PATRICK SPAUSTER **July 2022** 

Georgina and Charlotte Bloomberg Public Service Fellow Master's of Urban Planning Candidate, NYU Wagner Graduate Student Researcher, NYU Furman Center

Phone: 203-448-0855; email: patrick.spauster@gmail.com | ps4375@nyu.edu

Linkedin: www.linkedin.com/in/patrick-spauster Personal Website: www.patrickspauster.com

#### **Career Brief**

Patrick Spauster is a journalist, data scientist, and researcher focusing on urban and housing issues. Spauster is a Georgina and Charlotte Bloomberg Public Service Fellow and Master's of Urban Planning Candidate at the Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service. He currently writes for Bloomberg News and CityLab as a data journalist, researches housing policy at the Furman Center at New York University, and serves as editor-in-chief of Wagner's Planning publication, the Wagner Planner. Before that he was a Research Analyst in the Metropolitan Housing and Communities Center at the Urban Institute. Spauster works on research projects and writes data-driven journalistic pieces related to rent relief, renter protections, homelessness, housing affordability, housing vouchers, housing discrimination, fair housing, and zoning. He has a strong background in quantitative methods, including analysis of survey, census, administrative, spatial, and program data in R, Stata, and Python. He visualizes data in R, QGIS, D3, and Illustrator and develops webpages in HTML, CSS, and Javascript. Spauster also has extensive qualitative research experience, planning and conducting interviews, coding research findings, and drawing out key themes, quotes, and insights. He is a strong writer experienced with many different written products, including long form research reports, opeds, briefs, fact sheets, blogs, and short articles. He supports teams by managing projects and timelines, presenting results, and communicating with partners and stakeholders. His past work focused on access to homeownership, foreclosure, climate resiliency, cash transfers, and human rights. Spauster holds a BA in Public Policy and a Minor in Economics from Davidson College, where he was a leader in the service community on campus.

#### Education

Expected 2023 Robert F. Wagner Graduate School of Public Service, New York University, New

York City, NY

M.S. Candidate, Urban Planning

Georgina and Charlotte Bloomberg Public Service Fellow

2017 Davidson College, Davidson, NC

B.A., Interdisciplinary Major in Public Policy, Economics Minor

### **Professional Experience**

2022 Bloomberg News, New York, NY

Data Journalism Intern

- Pitched, sourced, and wrote stories on general data assignment team for Bloomberg News verticals
- Regular CityLab contributor
- Lead writing and data analysis for investigation of the rise in Starbucks unions
- Create publication-ready maps and graphics using R, Excel, QGIS, and Adobe Illustrator

2021-Furman Center, New York University, New York, NY **Graduate Student Researcher** 

- Data analyst programming in R and Python
- Analyzed housing production and subsidy data, wrote sections of the

- report, and created interactive housing development leaflet map for "State of the City 2022"
- Evaluate the Impact of New York's 2019 rent protection law on multifamily lending using property records and HMDA data
- Use unemployment and census data to target areas most in need of Emergency Rental Assistance payments
- Conduct data analysis and create maps, visualizations, and graphics
- Write and edit reports, blogs, briefs, and other products

2018-2021

Urban Institute, Metropolitan Housing and Communities Center, Washington, DC Research Analyst (2021)

Research Assistant (2018-2020)

- Conduct qualitative, quantitative, and mixed mehods research projects on fair housing, homelessness, vouchers, and zoning.
- Manage projects and budgets, meetings, logistics, and events.
- Clean, manage, analyze, and automate large datasets in R and Stata
- Create maps, data visualizations, and graphics
- Conduct interviews, draft interview protocols, and code research findings
- Write and edit reports, blogs, briefs, and other products

2017-

Prose Media, New York, NY

Freelance Writer

- Wrote dozens of blog posts, reviews, and other short pieces for clients
- Focused on clear, condensed writing designed for search engine optimization

2017-2018

The Center for New York City Neighborhoods, New York, NY Program Associate

- Provided relief and support to housing insecure citizens. Staffed the Center's homeowner hub, managed housing cases, provided counseling referral services, and leveraged program partnerships through the NYS Mortgage Assistance Program, Build it Back, Flood Help NY, and Temporary Housing Services.
- Supported research on NYC projects to improve agency programs in foreclosure mitigation, climate resilience, and access to homeownership.
- Analyzed organizational caller data patterns and created plan to increase responsiveness
- Served on the agency's disaster response committee in the wake of hurricanes Harvey, Irma, and Maria

2016

Human Rights Watch, New York, NY Children's Rights Division Intern,

- Assisted researchers and executives with research, writing, editing, and administration for children's rights research projects
- Composed treaty body on Bangladesh submitted for review of the United Nations Committee on Elimination of Discrimination against Women; Composed background research report on Peruvian Gold Mining
- Contributed significant research, writing, and editing and for nine country profiles for Education Under Attack 2018, a report of the Global Coalition to Protect Education from Attack

#### Fellowships, Honors, and Awards

Georgina and Charlotte Bloomberg Public Service Fellow, 2021-2023;

Ten Urban Wire Blog Posts that Elevated the Debate, 2018;

Davidson College Civic Engagement Council Chairperson, 2016-2017;

Leadership Davidson Selectee, 2017;

Vann Center for Ethics Human Rights Watch Fellow, 2016.

## **Technical Skills**

R Web development Interviewing Stata Illustrator Focus groups ArcGIS/QGIS Data visualization Data walks Python Blogging Mapping

nVivo Wordpress web design Freelance writing Qualtrics **Econometrics** Opinion editorial HTML/CSS Investigative reporting Regression

Web scraping Javascript/JQuery Program evaluation D3

Ethnography Editing

#### **Publications**

#### Articles

Patrick Spauster, "The Bitter Fight for Unions at Starbucks, One Year Later," Bloomberg City, August 30, 2022.

Patrick Spauster, "Gainesville, Florida, Moves to End Single-Family Zoning," Bloomberg CityLab, August 9, 2022.

Patrick Spauster, "A College Town Takes on Exclusionary Zoning," Bloomberg CityLab, July 28, 2022.

Patrick Spauster, "Cities Seek Alternatives to Gas Tax Holidays," Bloomberg CityLab, July 1, 2022.

#### **Blog Posts**

Eldridge, Matthew, Kimberly Burrowes, and Patrick Spauster, "How Cities Like Birmingham, Alabama, Are Unlocking New Funding for Parks and Green Space," Urban Wire (blog), February 18, 2019.

Scally, Corianne, Camille Anoll and Patrick Spauster, "Four lessons on federal crisis response from ten years of foreclosure counseling," Urban Wire (blog), May 23, 2017.

Spauster, Patrick, "LeBron James's I Promise School puts a public face to the evidence-based approach of whole-family intervention," Urban Wire (blog), August 14, 2018.

Spauster, Patrick, "In some New York City districts, nearly one in four students experience homelessness," Urban Wire (blog), Urban Wire, November 19, 2018.

Spauster, Patrick, "LeBron James's Foundation Is Building Transitional Housing at the I Promise School. But It Can Go Further to Help Families," Urban Wire (blog), November 22, 2019.

Spauster, Patrick, "Three Things We Learned from Cleaning One Million DMV Property Records," Data@Urban (blog), December 3, 2019.

Spauster, Patrick, "Tackling Systemic Barriers in Northeast Buffalo to Help Break Cycles of Poverty," Urban Wire (blog), December 16, 2019.

Spauster, Patrick, Mica O'Brien, and Olivia Fiol, "The Suburbs Aren't Under Attack. They Can Be Places of Opportunity for All," Urban Wire (blog), September 11, 2020.

#### **Opeds**

Patrick Spauster, "New York City Needs Basement Apartments Now More Than Ever," City Limits, September 30, 2021.

### **Published Reports**

- Anderson, Theresa, Susan J. Popkin, Marla McDaniel, Amelia Coffey, Amanda Gold, **Patrick Spauster**, Peace Gwam, Marcus Gaddy, and Adaeze Okoli. Investing in Equitable Urban Park Systems. 2021. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/developing-two-generation-approaches-communities">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/developing-two-generation-approaches-communities</a>
- Cunningham, Mark K., Devlin Hanson, Sarah Gillespie, Mike Pergamit, Alyse D. Oneto, **Patrick Spauster**, Tracey O'Brien, Liz Sweiter, Christine Velez Breaking the Homelessness-Jail Cycle with Housing First: Results from the Denver Supportive Housing Social Impact Bond Initiative. 2021. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/breaking-homelessness-jail-cycle-housing-first-results-denver-supportive-housing-social-impact-bond-initiative">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/breaking-homelessness-jail-cycle-housing-first-results-denver-supportive-housing-social-impact-bond-initiative</a>
- Eldridge, Matthew, Kimberly Burrowes, and **Patrick Spauster**. Investing in Equitable Urban Park Systems. 2019. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/investing-equitable-urban-park-systems">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/investing-equitable-urban-park-systems</a>
- Galvez, Martha, Solomon Greene, Alyse Oneto, and **Patrick Spauster**. Protecting Housing Choice Voucher Holders from Discrimination: Lessons from Oregon and Texas. 2020. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/housing-and-land-use-implications-split-roll-property-tax-reform-california">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/housing-and-land-use-implications-split-roll-property-tax-reform-california</a>
- Gillespie, Sarah, Devlin Hanson, Alyse D. Oneto, **Patrick Spauster**, Mary Cunningham, Mike Pergamit. Denver Supportive Housing Social Impact Bond Initiative: Housing Stability Payments. 2020. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/denver-supportive-housing-social-impact-bond-initiative-housing-stability-payments-0">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/denver-supportive-housing-social-impact-bond-initiative-housing-stability-payments-0</a>
- Gillespie, Sarah, Devlin Hanson, Alyse D. Oneto, **Patrick Spauster**, Mary Cunningham, Mike Pergamit. Denver Supportive Housing Social Impact Bond Initiative: Final Outcome Payments. 2021. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. https://www.urban.org/research/publication/denversupportive-housing-social-impact-bond-initiative-final-outcome-payments
- Greene, Solomon, Laurie Goodman, Sarah Strochak, Daniel Teles, and **Patrick Spauster**. Housing and Land Use Implications of Split-Roll Property Tax Reform in California. 2020. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/housing-and-land-use-implications-split-roll-property-tax-reform-california">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/housing-and-land-use-implications-split-roll-property-tax-reform-california</a>
- Greene, Solomon, **Patrick Spauster**, Martha Galvez, and Daniel Teles. State and Local Voucher Protection Laws: Introducing a New Legal Dataset. 2020. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/state-and-local-voucher-protection-laws-introducing-new-legal-dataset">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/state-and-local-voucher-protection-laws-introducing-new-legal-dataset</a>
- Popkin, Susan, Theresa Anderson, Amelia Coffey, Marcus Gaddy, Charmaine Runes, Marla McDaniel, Adaeze Okoli, **Patrick Spauster**. Incorporation Two-Generation Approaches in Community Change. 2019. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/incorporating-two-generation-approaches-community-change">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/incorporating-two-generation-approaches-community-change</a>
- Scally, Corianne, Camille Anoll, Jung Choi, **Patrick Spauster**, Leah Hendey, Diane Levy, and Bing Bai. 2018. "Responding to a Crisis: The National Foreclosure Mitigatgion Counseling Program 2008-2018." NeighborWorks America. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/responding-crisis-national-">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/responding-crisis-national-</a>

#### foreclosure-mitigation-counseling-program-2008-2018

Scally, Corianne, Eric Burnstein, Nicole DuBois, Marcus Gaddy, Chris Hayes, Clare Saleno, **Patrick Spauster**, Yipeng Su, Elsa Falkenburger, and Susan Popkin. "Evaluation of the Resident Opportunity and Self-Sufficiency Service Coordinator Program." 2019. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/evaluation-resident-opportunity-and-self-sufficiency-service-coordinator-program">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/evaluation-resident-opportunity-and-self-sufficiency-service-coordinator-program</a>

Spauster, Patrick, Lydia Lo, and Yonah Freemark. The Rise of Market-Reliant Affordable Housing Tools. 2021. Washington, D.C.: The Urban Institute. <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/rise-market-reliant-affordable-housing-tools">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/rise-market-reliant-affordable-housing-tools</a>

#### **Features**

Cunningham, Mark K., Devlin Hanson, Sarah Gillespie, Mike Pergamit, Alyse D. Oneto, **Patrick Spauster**, and Josh Leopold "Reenvisioning Rural America," Urban Institute, September 2021, <a href="https://www.urban.org/research/publication/promise-heights-response-challenges-created-covid-19">https://www.urban.org/research/publication/promise-heights-response-challenges-created-covid-19</a>

Scally, Corianne, Amanda Gold, Yipeng Su, Jorge Morales-Burnett, Eric Burnstein, and **Patrick Spauster**, "Housing First Breaks the Homelessness-Jail Cycle," Urban Institute, July 2021, https://www.urban.org/features/housing-first-breaks-homelessness-jail-cycle

## **Presentations**

**Spauster, Patrick**, Solomon Greene, and Sarah Strochak "Housing and Land Use Implications of Proposed Split Roll Tax Reform," Fresno, CA and Washington DC. Zoom. July 30th, 2020.

**Spauster, Patrick** and Peter Tatian. "Building a Data-Driven Learning Culture." Washington, DC. Zoom. May 13<sup>th</sup>, 2020.

**Spauster**, **Patrick**, Timothy Tripplett, and Brett Theodos. "Improving Survey Design and Administration," Washington, DC. Zoom. August 11th, 2020.

# <u>Service</u>

Steward, GSOC-UAW Local 2110: The Union for Graduate Employees at NYU, 2022
Data Analyst, Unlock NYC, 2021-2022
Organizer, Urban Institute Employees Union, 2019-2021
Puerto Rico Evacuee Service Center Volunteer 2017-2018
Davidson College Civic Engagement Council Chairperson 2016-2017
Volunteer and Researcher with the Beatties Ford Road Project 2017
Vice President, Communications Davidson Nonprofit Consulting 2015-2017